<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "file://zonbook/docbookx.dtd"
[
    <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "file://AWSShared/common/xinclude.mod">
    %xinclude;
    <!ENTITY % phrases-shared SYSTEM "file://AWSShared/common/phrases-shared.ent">
    %phrases-shared;
    <!ENTITY % phrases-appmesh SYSTEM "../shared/phrases-app-mesh.ent"> 
    %phrases-appmesh;
]>
<section role="topic" id="tls">
    <info>
        <title id="tls.title">Transport Layer Security (TLS)</title>
        <titleabbrev>Transport Layer Security (TLS)</titleabbrev>
    </info>
    <para>In &MESH;, Transport Layer Security (TLS) encrypts communication between the Envoy proxies
        deployed on compute resources that are represented in &MESH; by &collective-resource-name;s,
        such as <link linkend="virtual_nodes" endterm="virtual_nodes.title"/> and <link
            linkend="virtual_gateways" endterm="virtual_gateways.title"/>. The proxy negotiates and
        terminates TLS. When the proxy is deployed with an application, your application code is not
        responsible for negotiating a TLS session. The proxy negotiates TLS on your application's
        behalf. </para>
    <para>&MESH; allows you to provide the TLS certificate to the proxy in the following
        ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>A private certificate from &ACMlong; (&ACM;) that is issued by an &PCAlong;
                (&PCA;).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A certificate stored on the local file system of a virtual node that is issued by
                your own certificate authority (CA) </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A certificate provided by a Secrets Discovery Service (SDS) endpoint over local Unix Domain Socket.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para><link linkend="proxy-authorization" endterm="proxy-authorization.title"/> must be enabled
        for the deployed Envoy proxy represented by a &collective-resource-name;. We recommend that
        when you enable proxy authorization, you restrict access to only the
        &collective-resource-name; that you're enabling encryption for.</para>
    <section id="virtual-node-tls-prerequisites">
        <info>
            <title id="virtual-node-tls-prerequisites.title">Certificate requirements</title>
        </info>
        <para>One of the Subject Alternative Names (SANs) on the certificate must match specific
            criteria, depending on how the actual service represented by a mesh endpoint is
            discovered. </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">DNS</emphasis> &endash; One of the certificate SANs must
                    match the value provided in the DNS service discovery settings. For an
                    application with the service discovery name
                            <code><replaceable>mesh-endpoint.apps.local</replaceable></code>, you
                    can create a certificate matching that name, or a certificate with the wild card
                            <code>*.<replaceable>apps.local</replaceable></code>.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">&CMAPlong;</emphasis> &endash; One of the certificate
                    SANs must match the value provided in the &CMAP; service discovery settings
                    using the format
                        <code><replaceable>service-name.namespace-name</replaceable></code>. For an
                    application with the &CMAP; service discovery settings of serviceName
                            <code><replaceable>mesh-endpoint</replaceable></code> and the
                    namespaceName <code><replaceable>apps.local</replaceable></code>, you can create
                    a certificate matching the name
                            <code><replaceable>mesh-endpoint.apps.local</replaceable></code>, or a
                    certificate with the wild card
                        <code>*.<replaceable>apps.local</replaceable>.</code></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For both discovery mechanisms, if none of the certificate SANs match the DNS service
            discovery settings, the connection between Envoys fails with the following error
            message, as seen from the client Envoy. </para>
        <programlisting role="nocopy">TLS error: 268435581:SSL routines:OPENSSL_internal:CERTIFICATE_VERIFY_FAILED</programlisting>
    </section>
    <section id="authentication-certificates">
        <info>
            <title id="authentication-certificates.title">TLS authentication certificates</title>
        </info>
        <para>&MESH; supports multiple sources for certificates when using TLS
            authentication.</para>
        <variablelist role="termdef">
            <varlistentry>
                <term>&PCA;</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The certificate must be stored in &ACM; in the same Region and &AWS; account
                        as the &collective-resource-name; that will use the certificate. The CA's
                        certificate does not need to be in the same &AWS; account, but it does still
                        need to be in the same Region as the &collective-resource-name;. If you
                        don't have an &PCAshort;, then you must <ulink type="documentation"
                            url="acm-pca/latest/userguide/PcaCreateCa.html">create one</ulink>
                        before you can request a certificate from it. For more information about
                        requesting a certificate from an existing &PCA; using &ACM;, see <ulink
                            type="documentation"
                            url="acm/latest/userguide/gs-acm-request-private.html">Request a Private
                            Certificate</ulink>. The certificate cannot be a public
                        certificate.</para>
                    <para>The private CAs that you use for TLS client policies must be root
                        CAs.</para>
                    <para>To configure a virtual node with certificates and CAs from &PCA;, the
                        principal (such as a user or role) that you use to call &MESH; must have the
                        following &IAM; permissions: </para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>For any certificates that you add to a listener's TLS
                                configuration, the principal must have the
                                    <code>acm:DescribeCertificate</code> permission.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>For any CAs configured on a TLS client policy, the principal must
                                have the <code>acm-pca:DescribeCertificateAuthority</code>
                                permission.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <important>
                        <para>Sharing CAs with other accounts may give those accounts unintended
                            privileges to the CA. We recommend using resource-based policies to
                            restrict access to just
                                <code>acm-pca:DescribeCertificateAuthority</code> and
                                <code>acm-pca:GetCertificateAuthorityCertificate</code> for accounts
                            that do not need to issue certificates from the CA.</para>
                    </important>
                    <para>You can add these permissions to an existing &IAM; policy that is attached
                        to a principal or create a new principal and policy and attach the policy to
                        the principal. For more information, see <ulink type="documentation"
                            url="IAM/latest/UserGuide/access_policies_manage-edit.html">Editing IAM
                            Policies</ulink>, <ulink type="documentation"
                            url="IAM/latest/UserGuide/access_policies_create-console.html">Creating
                            &IAM; Policies</ulink>, and <ulink type="documentation"
                            url="IAM/latest/UserGuide/access_policies_manage-attach-detach.html#add-policies-console"
                            >Adding IAM Identity Permissions</ulink>.</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>You pay a monthly fee for the operation of each &PCA; until you delete
                            it. You also pay for the private certificates you issue each month and
                            private certificates that you export. For more information, see <ulink
                                type="marketing" url="/certificate-manager/pricing/">&ACMlong;
                                Pricing</ulink>.</para>
                    </note>
                    <para>When you enable <link linkend="proxy-authorization">proxy
                            authorization</link> for the Envoy Proxy that a
                        &collective-resource-name; represents, the &IAM; role that you use must be
                        assigned the following &IAM; permissions:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>For any certificates configured on a virtual node’s listener, the
                                role must have the <code>acm:ExportCertificate</code>
                                permission.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>For any CAs configured on a TLS client policy, the role must have
                                the <code>acm-pca:GetCertificateAuthorityCertificate</code>
                                permission.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>File System</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can distribute certificates to Envoy using the file system. You can do
                        this by making the certificate chain and the corresponding private key
                        available on the file path. That way, these resources are reachable from the
                        Envoy sidecar proxy. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Envoy’s Secret Discovery Service (SDS)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Envoy fetches secrets like TLS certificates from a specific endpoint
                        through the Secrets Discovery protocol. For more information about this
                        protocol, see Envoy's <ulink
                            url="https://www.envoyproxy.io/docs/envoy/latest/configuration/security/secret"
                            >SDS documentation</ulink>.</para>
                    <para>App Mesh configures the Envoy proxy to use a Unix Domain Socket that's
                        local to the proxy to serve as the Secret Discovery Service (SDS) endpoint
                        when SDS serves as the source for your certificates and certificate chains.
                        You can configure the path to this endpoint by using the
                            <code>APPMESH_SDS_SOCKET_PATH</code> environment variable.</para>
                    <important>
                        <para>Local Secrets Discovery Service using Unix Domain Socket is supported
                            on &MESH; Envoy proxy version 1.15.1.0 and later.</para>
                        <para>&MESH; supports V2 SDS protocol using gRPC.</para>
                    </important>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Integrating with SPIFFE Runtime Environment (SPIRE)</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can use any sidecar implementation of the SDS API, including existing
                        toolchains like <ulink url="https://github.com/spiffe/spire">SPIFFE Runtime
                            Environment (SPIRE)</ulink>. SPIRE is designed to enable the deployment
                        of mutual TLS authentication between multiple workloads in distributed
                        systems. It attests the identity of workloads at runtime. SPIRE also
                        delivers workload-specific, short-lived, and automatically rotating keys and
                        certificates directly to workloads.</para>
                    <para>You should configure the SPIRE Agent as an SDS provider for Envoy. Allow
                        it to directly supply Envoy with the key material that it needs to provide
                        mutual TLS authentication. Run SPIRE Agents in sidecars next to Envoy
                        proxies. The Agent takes care of re-generating the short-lived keys and
                        certificates as required. The Agent attests Envoy and determines which
                        service identities and CA certificates that it should make available to
                        Envoy when Envoy connects to the SDS server exposed by the SPIRE
                        Agent.</para>
                    <para>During this process, service identities and CA certificates are rotated,
                        and updates are streamed back to Envoy. Envoy immediately applies them to
                        new connections without any interruptions or downtime and without the
                        private keys ever touching the file system.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>&ACMlong;&endash; &PCAlong; (&PCA;) can be used along side SPIRE
                                to serve as an upstream Certificate Authority. By using a Private
                                Certificate Authority (PCA), private keys for the CAs are hardware
                                based and not stored in the memory or on the disk. This adds an
                                additional layer of security. For more information, see the <ulink
                                    url="https://github.com/spiffe/spire/blob/master/doc/plugin_server_upstreamauthority_aws_pca.md"
                                    >SPIRE documentation</ulink>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section id="envoy-configuration-tls">
        <info>
            <title id="envoy-configuration-tls.title">How &MESH; configures Envoys to negotiate
                TLS</title>
        </info>
        <para>&MESH; uses the &collective-resource-name; configuration of both the client and server
            when determining how to configure the communication between Envoys in a mesh.</para>
        <variablelist role="termdef">
            <varlistentry>
                <term>With client policies</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When a client policy is enforcing the use of TLS, and one of the ports in
                        the client policy matches the port of the server's policy, the client policy
                        is used to configure the TLS validation context of the client. For example,
                        if a virtual gateway's client policy matches a virtual node's server policy,
                        TLS negotiation will be attempted between the proxies using the settings
                        defined in the virtual gateway's client policy. If the client policy does
                        not match the port of the server's policy, TLS between the proxies may or
                        may not be negotiated, depending on the server policy's TLS settings.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Without client policies</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If the client has not configured a client policy, or the client policy
                        does not match the port of the server, &MESH; will use the server to
                        determine whether or not to negotiate TLS from the client, and how. For
                        example, if a virtual gateway has not specified a client policy, and a
                        virtual node has not configured TLS termination, TLS will not be negotiated
                        between the proxies. If a client has not specified a matching client policy,
                        and a server has been configured with TLS modes <code>STRICT</code> or
                            <code>PERMISSIVE</code>, the proxies will be configured to negotiate
                        TLS. Depending on how the certificates have been provided for TLS
                        termination, the following additional behavior applies.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">&ACM;-managed TLS certificates</emphasis>
                                &endash; When a server has configured TLS termination using an
                                &ACM;-managed certificate, &MESH; automatically configures clients
                                to negotiate TLS and validate the certificate against the root CA
                                that the certificate chains up to.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">File-based TLS certificates</emphasis>
                                &endash; When a server has configured TLS termination using a
                                certificate from the proxy's local file system, &MESH; automatically
                                configures a client to negotiate TLS, but the certificate of the
                                server is not validated.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Subject alternative names</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can optionally specify a list of Subject Alternative Names (SANs) to
                        trust. SANs must be in the FQDN or URI format. If SANs are provided, Envoy
                        verifies that the Subject Alternative Name of the presented certificate
                        matches one of the names on this list.</para>
                    <para>If you don't specify SANs on the terminating mesh endpoint, the Envoy
                        proxy for that node doesn't verify the SAN on a peer client certificate. If
                        you don't specify SANs on the originating mesh endpoint, the SAN on the
                        certificate provided by the terminating endpoint must match the mesh
                        endpoint service discovery configuration.</para>
                    <para>For more information, see &MESH; <ulink
                            url="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/app-mesh/latest/userguide/tls.html#virtual-node-tls-prerequisites"
                            >TLS: Certificate requirements</ulink>.</para>
                    <important>
                        <para>&MESH; doesn't support wildcard DNS SANs. You need to provide exact
                            names of the endpoints.</para>
                    </important>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section id="verify-encryption">
        <info>
            <title id="verify-encryption.title">Verify encryption</title>
        </info>
        <para>Once you've enabled TLS, you can query the Envoy proxy to confirm that communication
            is encrypted. The Envoy proxy emits statistics on resources that can help you understand
            if your TLS communication is working properly. For example, the Envoy proxy records
            statistics on the number of successful TLS handshakes it has negotiated for a specified
            &collective-resource-name;. Determine how many successful TLS handshakes there were for
            a &collective-resource-name; named
                <code><replaceable>my-mesh-endpoint</replaceable></code> with the following
            command.</para>
        <programlisting><userinput>curl -s 'http://<replaceable>my-mesh-endpoint.apps.local</replaceable>:9901/stats' | grep ssl.handshake</userinput></programlisting>
        <para>In the following example returned output, there were three handshakes for the
            &collective-resource-name;, so communication is encrypted.</para>
        <programlisting role="nocopy">listener.0.0.0.0_15000.ssl.handshake: 3</programlisting>
        <para>The Envoy proxy also emits statistics when TLS negotiation is failing. Determine
            whether there were TLS errors for the &collective-resource-name;.</para>
        <programlisting><userinput>curl -s 'http://<replaceable>my-mesh-endpoint.apps.local</replaceable>:9901/stats' | grep -e "ssl.*\(fail\|error\)"</userinput></programlisting>
        <para>In the example returned output, there were zero errors for several statistics, so the
            TLS negotiation succeeded.</para>
        <programlisting role="nocopy">listener.0.0.0.0_15000.ssl.connection_error: 0
listener.0.0.0.0_15000.ssl.fail_verify_cert_hash: 0
listener.0.0.0.0_15000.ssl.fail_verify_error: 0
listener.0.0.0.0_15000.ssl.fail_verify_no_cert: 0
listener.0.0.0.0_15000.ssl.ssl.fail_verify_san: 0</programlisting>
        <para>For more information about Envoy TLS statistics, see <ulink
                url="https://www.envoyproxy.io/docs/envoy/latest/configuration/listeners/stats"
                >Envoy Listener Statistics</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="certificate-renewal">
        <info>
            <title id="certificate-renewal.title">Certificate renewal</title>
        </info>
        <formalpara>
            <title>&PCA;</title>
            <para>When you renew a certificate with &ACM;, the renewed certificate will be
                automatically distributed to your connected proxies within 35 minutes of the renewal
                completion. We recommend using managed renewal to automatically renew certificates
                nearing the end of their validity period. For more information, see <ulink
                    type="documentation" url="acm/latest/userguide/managed-renewal.html">Managed
                    Renewal for ACM's Amazon-Issued Certificates</ulink> in the &ACMlong; User
                Guide.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Your own certificate</title>
            <para>When using a certificate from the local file system, Envoy will not automatically
                reload the certificate when it changes. You may either restart or redeploy the Envoy
                process to load a new certificate. You can also place a newer certificate at a
                different file path and update the virtual node or gateway configuration with that
                file path.</para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <section id="mtls-configure-ecs">
        <info>
            <title id="mtls-configure-ecs.title">Configure &ECS; workloads to use TLS authentication
                with &MESHlong;</title>
        </info>
        <para>You can configure your mesh to use TLS authentication. Make sure that the certificates
            are available to Envoy proxy sidecars that you add to your workloads. You can attach an
            EBS or EFS volume to your Envoy sidecar, or you can store and retrieve certificates from
            &AWS; &ASMshort;.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you use file-based certificate distribution, attach an EBS or EFS volume to
                    your Envoy sidecar. Make sure that the path to the certificate and private key
                    matches the one that is configured in &MESHlong;.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you're using SDS-based distribution, add a sidecar that implements Envoy’s
                    SDS API with access to the certificate.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <note>
            <para>SPIRE is not supported on &ECS;.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section id="mtls-configure-kubernetes ">
        <info>
            <title id="mtls-configure-kubernetes.title">Configure Kubernetes workloads to use TLS
                authentication with &MESHlong;</title>
        </info>
        <para>You can configure the &MESHlong; Controller for Kubernetes to enable TLS
            authentication for virtual node and virtual gateway service backends and listeners. Make
            sure that the certificates are available to the Envoy proxy sidecars that you add to
            your workloads. You can see an example for each distribution type in the <ulink
                url="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/app-mesh/latest/userguide/mutual-tls.html#mtls-walkthrough"
                >walkthrough</ulink> section of Mutual TLS Authentication.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you use file-based certificate distribution, attach an EBS or EFS volume to
                    your Envoy sidecar. Make sure that the path to the certificate and private key
                    matches the one configured in the controller. Alternatively, you can use a
                    Kubernetes Secret that is mounted on the file system.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you’re using SDS-based distribution, you should setup a node local SDS
                    provider that implements Envoy’s SDS API. Envoy will reach it over UDS. To
                    enable SDS based mTLS support in the EKS AppMesh controller, set the
                        <code>enable-sds</code> flag to <code>true</code> and provide the local SDS
                    provider’s UDS path to the controller via the <code>sds-uds-path</code> flag. If
                    you use helm, you set these as part of your controller installation:
                    </para>
                <programlisting>--set sds.enabled=true</programlisting>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <note>
            <para>You won't be able to use SPIRE to distribute your certificates if you're using
                &EKSlong; (&EKS;) in &FARGATE; mode.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
</section>
