<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "file://zonbook/docbookx.dtd"
[
    <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "file://AWSShared/common/xinclude.mod">
    %xinclude;
    <!ENTITY % phrases-shared SYSTEM "file://AWSShared/common/phrases-shared.ent">
    %phrases-shared;
    <!ENTITY % phrases-appmesh SYSTEM "../shared/phrases-app-mesh.ent"> 
    %phrases-appmesh;
]>
<section role="topic" id="virtual_services">
    <info>
        <title id="virtual_services.title">Virtual services</title>
    </info>
    <para>A virtual service is an abstraction of a real service that is provided by a virtual node
        directly or indirectly by means of a virtual router. Dependent services call your virtual
        service by its <code>virtualServiceName</code>, and those requests are routed to the virtual
        node or virtual router that is specified as the provider for the virtual service.</para>
    <section id="create-virtual-service">
        <info>
            <title id="create-virtual-service.title">Creating a virtual service</title>
        </info>
        <para>To create a virtual service using the &CLI; version &aws_cli_min_version; or higher,
            see the example in the &CLI; reference for the <ulink type="documentation"
                url="cli/latest/reference/appmesh/create-virtual-service.html"
                >create-virtual-service</ulink> command. </para>
        <procedure>
            <title>To create a virtual service using the &console;</title>
            <step>
                <para>&MESHConsoleSwitch;</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Choose the mesh that you want to create the virtual service in. All of the
                    meshes that you own and that have been <link linkend="sharing">shared</link>
                    with you are listed.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Choose <guilabel>Virtual services</guilabel> in the left navigation.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Choose <guilabel>Create virtual service</guilabel>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>For <guilabel>Virtual service name</guilabel>, choose a name for your virtual
                    service. You can choose any name, but the service discovery name of the real
                    service that you're targeting, such as
                        <code>my-service.default.svc.cluster.local</code>, is recommended to make it
                    easier to correlate your virtual services to real services and so that you don't
                    need to change your code to reference a different name than your code currently
                    references. The name that you specify must resolve to a non-loopback IP address
                    because the app container must be able to successfully resolve the name before
                    the request is sent to the Envoy proxy. You can use any non-loopback IP address
                    because neither the app or proxy containers communicate with this IP address.
                    The proxy communicates with other virtual services through the names you’ve
                    configured for them in App Mesh, not through IP addresses that the names resolve
                    to.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>For <guilabel>Provider</guilabel>, choose the provider type for your virtual
                    service:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If you want the virtual service to spread traffic across multiple
                            virtual nodes, select <guilabel>Virtual router</guilabel> and then
                            choose the virtual router to use from the drop-down menu.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If you want the virtual service to reach a virtual node directly,
                            without a virtual router, select <guilabel>Virtual node</guilabel> and
                            then choose the virtual node to use from the drop-down menu.</para>
                        <note>
                            <para>&MESH; may automatically create a default Envoy route retry policy
                                for each virtual node provider that you define on or after &default-route-retry-policy-date;, even though you can't define such a policy through the &MESH; API.
                                For more information, see <xref linkend="default-retry-policy" endterm="default-retry-policy.title"
                                />.</para>
                        </note>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If you don't want the virtual service to route traffic at this time
                            (for example, if your virtual nodes or virtual router doesn't exist
                            yet), choose <guilabel>None</guilabel>. You can update the provider for
                            this virtual service later.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Choose <guilabel>Create virtual service</guilabel> to finish.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </section>
</section>
